<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Academia | Gudmundur Blog&amp;Bio</title>
    <link>https://gumeo.github.io/category/academia/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://gumeo.github.io/category/academia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Academia</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 13:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://gumeo.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Academia</title>
      <link>https://gumeo.github.io/category/academia/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leaving Academia</title>
      <link>https://gumeo.github.io/post/leaving-academia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gumeo.github.io/post/leaving-academia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-choices-we-make&#34;&gt;The choices we make!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the major decisions that has haunted me through my PhD is whether I want to stay in academia or not. I sincerely love doing research, I love going to conferences, I love reading scientific papers and talking to other scholars. I even love giving talks and teaching, dissemination can be very rewarding and enjoyable. At some point I was certain that I would go for an academic career, but things change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing I like is a fresh challenge. After having spent the summer at deCODE genetics, I saw the possibilities outside academia. Doing a PhD is a binary process, either you have a PhD or not (&lt;em&gt;Quote from my friend Óli Páll, who recited Professor Havard Rue from NTNU&lt;/em&gt;). Having obtained my PhD made me think differently about my own future, and what I could accomplish. We sometimes say, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;it is the journey, not the destination&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, I feel that doing a PhD is different, there is a certain destination, obtaining the degree! In that regard I did not allow myself to ponder other possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is good to evaluate your goals and values every now and then. I have certain goals that I would like to achieve 5, 10 and 20 years down the line. From my point of view, I have a higher likelihood of achieving these goals outside academia, at least if I stay there for some time. I would also feel good about returning to academia at some point, having experienced the outside world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the important things my PhD supervisor made me realize is that the most valuable resource we possess is time. Time is a resource that we can &lt;strong&gt;never&lt;/strong&gt; get back. We should use this resource to do something we believe in, do something that makes a difference and we enjoy. I am forever grateful for my experience and time at DTU, I will cherish the moments I had there for the rest of my life. But for me the time for a change is now, it is time to go somewhere else, meet new people, learn, grow and contribute to great things. I look forward to this new path and I am happy for the choice I made.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
